<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning to the inhabitants of the whole earth and perticulerly, or more especially, to the inhabitants of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the islands and places to the same belonging and adjoyning, as appearing to be now under the more present and imediate concerne hereof, and to the rest in their order and time / R.R.</title>
            <author>R. R. (Richard Robinson), b. 1628?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21519</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12361423</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12361423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60233</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60233)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 646:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning to the inhabitants of the whole earth and perticulerly, or more especially, to the inhabitants of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the islands and places to the same belonging and adjoyning, as appearing to be now under the more present and imediate concerne hereof, and to the rest in their order and time / R.R.</title>
                  <author>R. R. (Richard Robinson), b. 1628?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 13.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60233:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING TO THE INHABITANTS Of the whole Earth: And perticulerly, or more Eſpecially, to the Inhabitants of England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Ireland, and the Iſlands and places to the ſame belonging and Adjoyning, as appearing to be now under the more preſent and Imediate concerne hereof: And to the reſt in their order and time.</p>
            <p>R. R.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eze. <hi>3.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When I ſay unto the Wicked thou ſhalt ſurely die and thou giveſt him not warning nor Speakeſt to warn the wicked, from his wicked way, to ſave his life, the ſame wicked man ſhall die in his Iniquity but his Blood will I require at thy hand.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ver. <hi>19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Yet if thou warn the wicked and he turne not from his wickedneſſe, nor from his wicked way he ſhall die in his Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, But thou haſt delivered thy ſoul.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year. 167<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60233:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60233:2"/>
            <p>TO all the Nations Countries, Kingdomes, Tongues Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Languages that are upon the face of the whole earth, And perticularly and more nearly, to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of England and the Kingdomes, Countries, and Iſlands, to the ſame belonging, and adjoyning, and of all the Citys Towns, Villages, Hamblets, and Places thereof; unto you all and every one of you, high and low, Rich and Poor, bond and free, male, and female, Prieſt, and People, Profeſſors, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faine, even from the King that ſits upon his Throne, unto the Begger upon the Dunghil; This is the word and Invitation of the Lord God, and a warning unto you by my mouth, that you all and every one of you who are found in unrighteouſneſſe unho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, or uncleanneſſe, of any kind, do ſpeedily repent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn every man from the evill of his ways, and from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that is in his hands, and by a due repentance, haſt to meet the Lord God in all holineſſe of life and uprightneſſe of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, if ſo be that you may eſcape, and that you periſh not; and be ye cleanſed, and purged, and cleanſe, and purge, all your ſtreets broad places, and high wayes, and all your Markets, Chanells, waterſewers, and gutters; as in the outward; ſo in the inward, your very hearts, from all thoſe filthy naſtie ſtinking noyſome ill ſavours of ſin iniquty, uncleanneſſe, perſecution, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and unholineſſe; with which as with a filthy naſtie noyſom ill ſavour your ſaid ſtreets, Townes, Steeplehouſes, and other places abounds: that ſo an high way in holineſſe may be made for our God (who is a conſumeing fire; and whoſe eyes is purer then to behold iniquity) to come down amongſt you; and make his progreſs through you, to take poſſeſſion of his own Inheritance (to wit) the heart of man, which ſhould be filled with righteouſneſſe, and be made the habitation of his holineſſe, and to ſee what this is, that the Children of men is a doing; and what it is, that this great Buſle, and Stirr that is amongſt them is about; for there hath been for a long time much profeſſion made amongſt the ſons and daughters of men, ſome prepareing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60233:3"/>and inventing, or ſetting up one way, or form of worſhip to come to the Father by, (as they pretended, and by which they might eſcape the wrath to come) and ſome an other; and every of the ſaid ſeverall ſorts of profeſſors, killing rending, tearing, riveing and diſtroying another, about what they have ſo ſet up and invented, becauſe they will not be of the ſame way or cannot be of the ſame perſwaſion with them. Symenting what they have ſo ſet up, with one anothers blood, and not onely with one an others blood, but even every ſort of them (as it were with open mouth) have run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the heritage of the Lord, if poſſible to diſtroy them, one building a wall and another daubing it with untempered morter; and thus like the Babell builders of old, hath every perſwaſion, or ſeverall ſort of profeſſors, endeavoured to ſet up a Tower, and build ſomething whoſe top, ſhould reach unto heaven, and be a deliverance unto them: And great ſtirr havock ſpoyl de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and bloodſhed, hath there been made, about the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall wayes, worſhips, and profeſſions ſo ſet up and invented; But now the Lord God of life and power (as in the days of old when the Babell builders aforeſaid was at their Confuſed work) is come and a comeing down amongſt you, to ſee what this is, that the Children of men is a doing, and will certainely, not onely break down and confound the work, but alſo ſcatter and deſtroy the workmen, And confound that Language, in which you do pretend to worſhip him; For though you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your ſelves may differ ſomthing in the form and manner of your profeſſions and pretence of worſhiping God, yet in the root and ground of evil (to wit) pride, perſecution, unholineſſe, and unrighteouſneſſe, you are one; And therefore now all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that are upon the face of the whole earth, I dearly deſire you ſeriouſly to conſider, if This Meſſage or warning which now comes to you, in the name of the Lord God, (to call you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and to forewarne you to fly, from the wrath that is likely with ſpeed to come upon you, who are found in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60233:3"/>Except you repent and return and be reconſiled and meet the Lord by a holy life and converſation); Were the meſſage and requeſt of your outward King, by his Meſſenger or harbenger unto you to give you notice of his approach unto you, And intended progreſs through your Towns Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and wayes, with requeſt to make proviſion and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment for him, or otherwiſe, that he would be offended with you, and do ſome iniury to you? Oh with what promt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and readineſſe [conſider] would you beſtirr your ſelves, to prepare for his approach and to give reception unto him: how would you dreſs and cleanſe your ſtreets Pavements, and channells, and ſcour and make clean your high wayes, Gutters, Waterſewers, and ſinks, (by which he ſhould paſs) and remove and purge out, all the dirt filth ſtinck and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ill ſavours out, all the ſame? and how would you deck and adorne your ſelves in your moſt cleane and Sumptious apparell, to meet and give entertainement unto him, and ſweep, dreſs, and perfume, your beſt Roomes for his recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and with what Obſequiouſnes and humility would you come before him and preſent your ſelves unto him, and do what elſe you thought might pleaſe him: and if you would doe all this and much more (if it were poſſible) for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement of your outward King, In how much more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, holy, lowly, Proſtrate, heavenly, and Obedient Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ought you to be prepared, to ſtand before and give en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to ſo Glorious a King as is the heavenly God, whoſe eyes is purer then to behold Iniquity and no unclean thing can ſtand before him, Who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and before whom all the Nations of the earth is but as the drop of a Bucket, who (as was ſaid before) is now come or a coming amongſt you, and will make his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs through you, that he may render to every man, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as his works ſhall be, Tribulation and anguiſh, to every ſoule that doth not righteouſly, and therefore, how clean
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60233:4"/>ought your garments (even the coverings of your ſpirits or ſpirituall coverings) in all holineſſe to be, and how become<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and needfull it is for you [conſider] to have your hearts (which ſhould be the habitation of God) purged and made clean, from all thoſe foul runing inward evills; and filthy, naſtie, noyſome, ill ſavours; of ſin and uncleanneſſe, with which you are polluted; and your whole man redeemed out of and from, all thoſe your vain converſations and evill prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes [to wit] Pride, lying, drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, curſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whoring, gaming, wantonneſſe, and all thoſe other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations with which (notwithſtanding your ſeverall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions) your ſaid Countrys, Citys, Towns, Villages, Streets, Steeple-houſes, and places, in too large a meaſure abounds; for is it not a ſhame unto you and to your ſeverall profeſſions, nay to the very name of Chirſtianity, to ſee, what pride and gaudineſſe, lying, ſwearing, curſing, drinking, whoring, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowſing debaucherys, and all manner of evills, &amp; abominations, are to be found, ſeen, and heard amongſt you, and in your ſaid Countryes, Citys, Towns, ſtreets, Steeple-houſes, and places, ſo that it may be truly ſaid of theſe and the like evills, as the prophet Jeremiah ſaid of ſwearing <hi>Jer:</hi> 23. that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of theſe things the Land mournes; and therefore as a warning and Meſſage from the Lord God, I cannot or dare not, but give you notice, And warn and Charge you as you love your Eternall good, that with all ſpeed you fly theſe things before ſpoken of; and all other the crying ſins and abominations, with which God is diſpleaſed, and of which in too large a meaſure, you are too deeply Guilty; For my Freinds, minde but your ſelves, and looke back upon your converſations and practices; and that with a ſerious eye, and you ſhall ſee, that the old world and Sodom, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the evill generations that have gone before you, and whom the Lord God condemned and out of, for their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities; was never more unrighteous or did abound with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60233:4"/>more abominations, then this generation even your ſelves doth: For oh! the Lying, Swearing, Whordomes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheryes, and Prophamneſs of all ſorts that is to be found among you, are almoſt Innumerable, therefore waſh you make you clean; put away the evil of your doings, from before the Lord, be afflicted and mourn, let your laughter be turned into mourning, and your Joy into heavineſs; for the Lord God hath a controverſie with the Inhabitants of the earth, becauſe of Lying, and Swearing, and comitting of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and blood toucheth blood; and therefore come out of them, and bring forth fruits meet for repentance and that with ſpeed, and think not that your profeſſions, (which ſtands in the unrighteouſneſs) will ſave you; But let righteouſneſs run down your ſtreets as ſtreams, and uprightneſs and truth as mighty rivers, that ſo the refuge of lyes (and of all other abominations, of which you are guilty,) may be ſwept away, and mind that of God in your own conſciences which ſhews you ſin and evill and be obedient thereunto, that if poſſible you may eſcape the Lords wrath, that you periſh not, for I teſtifie unto you that if you do not fly theſe things before ſpoken of, and all other the crying evills, and abominations of which you are and have been too deeply guilty, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of which the wrath of God comes upon upon the child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of diſobedience; and which makes you and your profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions, even to ſtinck and become abominable before the Lord; and get under the hollow of his hand, and ſhaddow of his wings by a due repentance, and ceaſe to do evill and learn to do well, and break the bonds of wickedneſs, and let the oppreſſed go free, and break every yoak; the Lord God will even come againſt you, and will even ſweep you with the Beſom of diſtruction, and that ſpeedly, except you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; and he will even deliver his People out of your mouths, that they may be a prey and ſpoyl to you no longer: And therefore dear people of all ſorts, eſpecially within this my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60233:5"/>native country of <hi>England,</hi> And the Countryes Places, and Iſles thereto belonging, and Adjoyning, Conſider, and whileſt you have a time lay it to heart; for the Lord God (concerning many of you laſt before named) hath even ſworn by his holineſs and hath ſaid he will not repent; that it ſhall ſurely come to paſs; And that though <hi>Noah, Abraham, David, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> were amongſt you or in the midſt of you, and did offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſtand in the Gap, yet they ſhould deliver no more by their righteouſneſſe ſave every one his own ſoule; ſo be warned and whileſt you have time Prize it, this is a viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you therefore ſleight it not.</p>
            <p>And now my deare friends unto you, in all nations, who in obedience to the principle of life and righteouſneſſe made manifeſt in you have forſaken, and are a forſakeing, the broad way and paths that leads to diſtruction, and thoſe many and groſs abominations before mentioned, which cauſeth the wrath of God to come upon the children of diſobedience, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to you, who are in Scorne called Quakers; who have heard and do hear the voyce of the true Shepheard and hath followed the ſame, in coming out of the many wayes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions into the one way Chriſt Jeſus; Keep in the ſame even way and Path, I dearly deſire you, (for unto you alſo this Meſſage reacheth,) that none of you may be found ſcattered abroad from under the true ſhelter, even the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, or out of the Sheep-coat and fold of reſt, but that you may with all ſpeed (even as Sheep runs after their ſhepherd, when they hear his voice and Call,) Get under the Shaddow of the Lords wings and under the hollow of his hand, and fly thither even as Bees doth to their hive, and as travelling men doth under the ſhaddow of a great Tree or other covert, when they perceive, the approach of an enſueing great Storm, or Shower, that they may find ſafety: Even ſo fly yee; unto him in whom ſafety is found. And haſt, haſt I dearly deſire every one, that is abroad (if any ſuch there be) from out of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60233:5"/>the open Fields and places, and from off the high Mountains and hills, where there is no Shelter, and come into the low Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyes and under the Roofe of God even the ſhelter and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of his holineſs, that you may be ſafe when the deſtroying Angel paſſeth over; For you know, or may be perſwaded, that they who are under a good Roofe or Covert, and there abides, may be and are often ſafe, from abiding the extremity of that Storme or Shower, which they that are abroad in the open Fields and without ſhelter muſt ſuſtaine: And therefore let none be ſtrayed from their Habitation (I dearly deſire) but all keep within their Tents, haveing the Lintall and ſide poſts of their homes, ſtricken with the blood of Sprinkling, That when he who ſmote the firſt born of <hi>Egypt</hi> goeth forth, you may be ſafe; And not only ſafe but alſo ready, having your Loynes girded, your Staff in your hand and your ſhooes on your feet, that you may goe on with him, into whatſoever State, Condition or Service of Holyneſs the Lord God ſhall call you to, being cloathed in righteouſneſs and having your Garments made clean in the blood of the Lamb, even ſuch, as in which it may be lawful for you, to behold your King the Lord God of hoſts; being purged from all ſpots and ſtaynes, and made white, having your Lamps trimed and lights burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that when the Cry comes, you may enter in, And none be ſhut out of the Bride Chamber.</p>
            <p>And my Deare Friends, It lyes further weightily upon me to ſignifie unto you, That the Lord God of Eternall life and power, doth intend and is about, to make his great, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, heavenly progreſs, throughout, and to the uttmoſt ends of all the Earth, And hath Choſen or Elected you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Nations of Them that dwell upon the face of the ſame earth, to be his Attendants, and to wait upon him, in his ſo great and glorious, and heavenly a progreſs, And hath or doth further lay it upon me, in his living everlaſting power and by the arm of his Eternal Authority, to warn and Charge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60233:6"/>and Cite, and Summon you all, and every one of you, high and low, Rich and poor, bond and free, Male and Female, That you and every one of you, (according to your ſeveral meaſures and guifts, and according to every ones ſeveral Condition and Calling, whereunto the Lord God hath called and begifted you) be, and perſonally appear in Spirit before him, and give your Spiritual Attendance upon him, and that in ſuch an holy, upright and undeſiled way, and after ſuch an humble, lowly, proſtrate, dilligent, heavenly, and obedient manner, as is ſuteable to your duty, and doth become the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Majeſtie and purity of ſo holy and heavenly, a God, as he is with whom we have to do, That ſo the everlaſting God, in all things may be glorified by you, and his truth and great name, be by, or through none diſgraced, that ſo he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to do you good, and call you up higher, and make you further pertakers of his manifold graces, which are yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and which he hath yet laid up in ſtore in Chriſt Jeſus, for all them that love him, and who are the called Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his purpoſe, And who do follow him in the Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, haveing their garments waſhed in the Blood of the Lamb, For (as it is written,) it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be, But when he ſhall appear, then ſhall we alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with him in Glory; So mind to keep in, and to that which is pure, And which you have known from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that when he comes whoſe Reward is with him, to give to every man according as his work ſhall be, you may none of you come ſhort, but every one (if it be poſſible) Enter into the Joy of his Lord: For conſider if an outward King do but Summon his Servants, or Subjects, to give their attendance upon him in his outward progreſs, with what readineſs, and willingneſs, will they appear before him, and in how Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and accompliſhed manner, will they endeavour to wait upon him that they may receive acceptance with him and (if poſſible) gaine preferment from him: And if it be ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60233:6"/>done in the outward by the Servants, or Subjects of an external Prince, let not us who are the ſervants, and who ſhould be the Subjects of a Heavenly King, come ſhort of our inward Duty, and obedience to the holy God, whoſe eyes is purer then to behold iniquity, and who is a liberall rewarder of all them that come unto him, and that wait upon him in truth and with an upright heart: And therefore my dear Friends, if any thing of the old ſtuffe, nature, or leaven yet remain in any, to hinder in this behalf, and if the Room (which is the heart, where the Lord ſhould lodge, and finde entertainment in this his Spiritual progreſs, be not yet throughly ſwept, cleanſed, purged, garniſhed, and perfumed, for the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and entertainment, of ſo holy and heavenly a gueſt, now while we have the Light to ſee, and the beſom (which is the power of God) to ſweep, let us haſt to dreſs the ſame, that if it be poſſible (my dear friends) we may none of us come ſhort (according to our ſeverall meaſures) of doing our duty to, and waiting upon ſo holy a God as him with whom we have to doe, and who is now calling and Inviteing unto a moſt near and heavenly attendance upon him:</p>
            <p>And my friends though the ſtorm may appear to be great, and the tempeſt that is likely to overtake the wicked (except they repent) exceeding terrible, yet be not diſmayed, for it is not intended to ſcatter the wheat but to refine it, and to blow away the Chaff, and ſever that which is intended for the wrath, from the pure grain; Dear Friends this comes to give warning and diſcharge a Duty, and not to reflect on any; And therefore haſt haſt I dearly deſire, And let none think light of what is ſaid, or look on it as being not of their Concern, but every one up, get upon your watch-tower. That when the Lord comes you may be ready, and when he ſpeaks you may hear.</p>
            <p>And now there is another ſort of People amongſt the Sons and daughters or men, unto whom alſo this Meſſage and Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60233:7"/>of the Lord reacheth, and thoſe are they, who (not out of hatred to the Lords truth, or envie to his people,) ſtands a far off, from the ſame, yet are not ſo bad as the worſt, neither runs with them to the ſame excceſs of ryot, nor are of the like perſecuting ſpirit with this generation, and doe many of them, even in their hearts wiſh well to the Iſrael of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that their latter end might be like his, And have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, even in heart mourned over the afflictions and hard uſeage of the Lords People, and Simpathized with them in their Sufferings, and yet have not been willing to come under the Croſs of Chriſt, and to ſuffer Afflictions with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, but have rather choſen to Imbrace this preſent evil world, and continue in the Faſhions and Cuſtomes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, though many of them hath not been without reproofes and often Alarmed, with ſomething that hath ſounded from under the Alter in their eares, whereby their peace, hath been many times broken, And they forced to look back, from off the Mountaines upon which they have been gone up: And unto all thoſe and every other amongſt the Sons and Daughters of men, who Breaths and Thirſts after Righteouſnes and longs after an acquaintance with the Lord and with his wayes; unto you I ſay, and it is the Invitation of the Lord, that you come away and follow the breathings of that in you, which Longs and Thuſts after Righteouſneſs, And ſtay no longer in the Vanities, Follyes, Faſhions, and Cuſtomes of the world, or any of the profeſſions thereof, But be ye Separate ſaith the Lord God, touch not the unclean thing, but follow the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, guidings, and directions, of that of God in their own Conſciences, which ſhews you ſin and evil, and the vanities and emptineſs of all things below him; And the Lord God will receive you; But if you ſtay any longer in this Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and will not be reclamed from their vaine converſations, and redeemed from the evills, and gathered from out of the Faſhions, Cuſtomes, Uncleanneſſes, and unrighteouſneſs of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60233:7"/>which they are guilty, you muſt be content to ſhare with them in their puniſhments; for he that will pertake with them in their ſins, Muſt pertake with them in their Plagues for the houre of their Judgments is come, And the Lamb the Lyon of the Tribe of Judah, hath made himſelfe ready, therefore fly for your lives (I dearely deſire you) and get you out of Sodom even this Wicked Generation, And from of the high Mountaines of Conceitednes upon which any of you are gone up, And get from under every green Tree, and falſe Reſt, into which you are gone, and under which you have ſought ſhaddow, And come, out fly unto the <hi>Zoar</hi> of God, the Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his holineſs, to his little flock, and that with ſpeed; Get out of the way of his Indignation and come under the mercy ſeat of God, for you are they, that yet ſtands in the Gap, and ſtops the ſtroke of Gods wrath, from falling upon the wicked, not becauſe the Lord hath beheld more holineſs or ſeen more uprightneſs in you, then in any of the ſons of men, But becauſe he hath a deſire to gather you, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend mercy unto you, for the breathing ſeed's ſake that is in you, And becauſe of the good, and kindneſs, forbearance, pity, and Compaſſion, that ſome of you (like <hi>Rahah</hi>) hath ſhewed to his People, even his little Flock, in ſcorne called Quakers, in the times of their ſufferings, which he doth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by proffer to Requite you for, (if you hear and obey,) by giving you Eternal Life, And by plucking you as brands out of that fire which is likely to fall upon the wicked: But then my friends you muſt come ſpeedily, and not ſtay lingering, Gods Spirit will not allwayes ſtrive with fleſh, Remember <hi>Lots</hi> wife. And you muſt not only make haſte, but you muſt alſo come in the right way, even by the footſteps of the Flock, in the ſelf denyal, and taking up the Croſs of Chriſt to your own wills, And to all thoſe deſires, Cuſtomes, and Faſhions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60233:8"/>(which are contrary to him,) And come to the plain Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage [thou and the] to a ſingle perſon, at which many of you have ſtumbled, And in all other things you muſt follow the footſteps of the flock, unto the Tent of the true ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, under whoſe roofe there is onely ſafety; Therefore fly thither I dearly deſire, and that with ſpeed, let none ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind or think light of what is ſaid: Remember Lot Sons in Law, who though they were warned, yet would not they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and therefore, eſcaped not the wrath, that was poured upon the wicked: But be ye not like the Horſe and Mule, that hath no underſtanding, but come away and that with ſpeed, and by the Right way: Fly for your lives, and now while you have time, and that a hand of Mercy is held out and extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you, Take the oppertunity, and Sleight it not: But if you will not obey, In haſting out of that, Aganſt which the wrath of God ſhall be revealed, yet Remember, that you have been warned, and know that your Diſtruction is of you ſelves, So while you have a time prize it, This is the day of your Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation.</p>
            <p>And thus dear people of all ſorts, and of all Nations, Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of this my Native Country of <hi>England,</hi> I hope I have Cleared my ſelfe of that which the Lord God in this behalf laid upon me, in warning the wicked to fly from their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, leaſt the wrath of God come ſpeedily upon them.</p>
            <p>And alſo in warning the flock of God, to keep in their fold and under the roof of their ſheep-coate, and that without ſtraying, that they may eſcape that Stormie ſhower which is likely to overtake ſuch as are abroad, or doe abide in the open fields without ſhelter.</p>
            <p>And alſo in warning ſuch as ſeems to halt between two opinions, and ſuch as breath after the Lord, and have not been ſo Cruell, but more kind then others, to the people of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60233:8"/>God, that they in and through obedience, to that of God in their Conſciences, which ſhews them ſin and evill, may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after the footſteps of the Lords flock, to feed with them and find harbour under the Tent of the trur Shepherd, that they may eſcape, and that they periſh not, I deſire that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one hereby Adviſed may be fully warned, and take the Oppertunity offered, and bring forth the fruits deſired, that they may eſcape (if poſſible) the Judgment threatned, that they Periſh not,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Priſon near <hi>Richmond</hi> 
                  <date>the 23 of the Second Month, 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>From your Real Friend and A well wiſher to all men. <hi>Richard Robinſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I deſire Friends to read this in their Meetings, and alſo diſperſe the ſame abroad (if poſſible) amongſt all Nations and to all People for my diſcharge.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errors that have eſcaped, the Preſs the Reader is deſired to amend.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>l</hi> 2. for, they pretended. <hi>r</hi> they have pretended <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l</hi> 15. for all <hi>r</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p</hi> 6. <hi>l</hi> 29. &amp; 30. <hi>r</hi> a travelling man. <hi>p</hi> 10. <hi>l</hi> 28. for their <hi>r</hi> your. <hi>p</hi> 11. <hi>l</hi> 11. <hi>r</hi> and come fly. <hi>l</hi> 24. <hi>r</hi> if you will hear. <hi>p</hi> 12. <hi>l</hi> 16. <hi>r</hi> is to be revealed.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
